in this video we're going to be talking
about stochastic volatility models in
quantitative finance here we'll be
talking about the people that have
contributed the who what why and when
and we're going to be investigating some
aspects of the models that are most
important
it all started in 1973 where investors
for many decades would be thanking the
work that went on in this year
this of course is the option pricing
model that was proposed by black and
shoals that actually had a closed form
solution of course the assumption here
is constant volatility
in 1976 the first stochastic volatility
models were actually produced by merton
and cox and ross
merton actually assumed a mixture of
continuous and jump processes while cox
and ross actually allowed for return
volatility to be a deterministic
function of underlying stock price
in 1976 the leverage effect was actually
found by black this is where we actually
compare the returns and the volatility
distributions and black worked out that
there's a negatively correlated
relationship between returns and
volatility although not really used for
evaluation in 1982 the arch model was
developed by engel to actually account
for the non-constant volatility
non-constant volatility is also called
heteroskedasticity and that's why the
model was called auto-regressive
conditional
heteroscedasticity and this really tried
to model the realized variances over
time
engel received the nobel prize for his
work
now an extension to the arch model was
actually developed by engel's phd
student boler's sleeve
now below sleeve tried to think about
how price changes not only depend on
past price changes but also on past
estimated volatility this extension to
the arch model involve using moving
averages
in 1987 the first stochastic volatility
model was made by helen white they
analyzed european call options on a
stock price subject to stochastic
volatility and using taylor series
expansion they derived an accurate
formula for call options this was
semi-closed with no correlation between
returns of volatility their assumption
was relaxed in 1988
now on monday the 19th of october 1987
the dow jones dropped more than 20
percent within one day and this would
later be called black monday
and since then the prevalence of
volatility smiles and smirks has been
evident in option markets and hence why
black shoals model in the use is very
controversial
in 1991 another stochastic volatility
model was created by stan and stein
these two worked on a unique method of
using a mean reverting process called
the einstein ulenbek process to actually
model variants
their original works assume no
correlation between returns and
volatilities
now in 1993 there was a very important
concept and this was the introduction of
the vix index at the time they were only
using the s p 100 and eight strikes on
puts and calls to determine the index
as well in 1993 a stochastic volatility
model was created by heston this
incorporated modeling a square root
process of variants the hester model is
a popular choice because of its easy
closed form solution that does require
numerical integration it has no negative
variances
and it incorporates the leverage effect
first identified by black in 1994 a
local volatility model was proposed by
de pere
now this is where market prices were
used to actually determine this local
volatility surface in terms of time and
strike this deterministic surface could
be used to value other options
incredibly at the same time derman and
carney were working on a similar model
this perfectly fits observed volatility
surface
in 1996
this man on the left-hand side came up
with a new way of thinking about
stochastic volatility
he actually created a jump diffusion and
stochastic volatility model
bates used the best aspects of the
heston's 1993 model in merton's jump
model in 1994
and then incorporated this in-between
stochastic volatility with jump
diffusion
this led to a new area of research
in 1998
rough volatility models were created by
compti and renault
this is where
the use of fractional brownian motion
was used to actually measure long-term
persistent memory in markets
in
2002 realized variants was investigated
by bond off nielsen and shepard
they created a new way to actually
estimate real world variances
this was incredible because of the
incorporation of high frequency data
in 2003
a new way and methodology of actually
creating the vix index came about
this was an update from the previous use
of s p 100 options
and now incorporated s p 500 as the
weighted prices of different puts and
calls
in 2004 the introduction of vix futures
by cboe was based on the fix index and
suddenly allowed for an increased amount
of risk management and volatility
trading
in 2006 cboe introduced vix options and
this also increased the pool of which
trading strategies could be developed
for risk management purposes and
volatility trading
2008 was very historic in terms of the
vix index
whereby the index reached its highest
intraday point at 89.53
on october the 24th
[Music]
in 2009 the double heston model by
christopherson heston and jacobs was
developed
this is where model in two variances
processes and one actually turns the
correlation between returns and
volatility stochastic this was a major
advancement in stochastic volatility
models now although we've covered a lot
in this video from 1973 all the way to
2009 there are many more models
including the cev and sabah models the
3-2 and the 4-2 models local stochastic
volatility models stochastic volatility
models with jumps exponential levy
models and svi parameterization etc
the current benchmarks seem to be
modelers that are actually based on
variance curves and skew modeling now
creating a video that incorporated all
of the stochastic volatility models
would have been a fool's errand but
hopefully this actually served to just
introduce the concept of stochastic
volatility models since the start of
option valuation in 1973 with a black
shoals model
now if you enjoyed the video please give
it a thumbs up and check out my channel
where we actually go through all things
quantitative finance